Like many of you here, I am trying to contribute
أحاول المساهمة ، كما هو الحال مع العديد منكم
towards a renaissance in Africa.
نحو النهوض بأفريقا
The question of transformation in Africa
مسألة التغيير في أفريقيا هي
really is a question of leadership.
بالفعل مسألة متعلقة بالقيادة.
Africa can only be transformed by enlightened leaders.
يمكن للقادة المستنيرين فقط تغيير أفريقيا
And it is my contention that the manner in which
ونضالي في ذلك الإطار الذي فيه
we educate our leaders is fundamental
نعلّم قادتنا هو امر اساسي
to progress on this continent.
للتقدم في هذه القارة.
I want to tell you some stories that explain my view.
أود إطلاعكم على بعض القصص لتبين وجهة نظري
We all heard about the importance of stories yesterday.
جميعنا سمع بالأمس عن أهمية القصص
An American friend of mine this year volunteered as a nurse in Ghana,
فقد تطوعت صديقتي الأمريكية هذه السنة كممرضة في غانا
and in a period of three months she came to a conclusion
و خلال ثلاث اشهر استنتجت
about the state of leadership in Africa
شيئا حول وضع القيادة في أفريقياء
that had taken me over a decade to reach.
لم أستطيع إستنتاجه إلا بعد عقد كامل
Twice she was involved in surgeries
شاركت مرتان في عمليات جراحية
where they lost power at the hospital.
عندما انقطع التيار الكهربائي في المستشفى
The emergency generators did not start.
ولم يعمل المولد الإحتياطي
There was not a flashlight, not a lantern, not a candle --
ولم يكن هناك كاشف ضوئي ولا فانوس ولا حتى شمعة
pitch black.
كان ظلاماً حالكاً
The patient's cut open, twice.
المريض لم يضمد جرحه ،، مرتان
The first time it was a C-section.
في المرة الأولى كانت عملية قيصيرة
Thankfully, baby was out -- mother and child survived.
حمداً لله ، كان قد ولد الطفل و كلاهما نجا
The second time was a procedure that involved local anesthesia.
وفي المرة الثانية كانت عملية تتطلب التخدير الموضعي
Anesthetic wears off. The patient feels pain.
انتهى تأثير التخدير . وبدأ المريض يشعر بالألم
He's crying. He's screaming. He's praying.
قام بالبكاء .. والصراخ .. والدعاء
Pitch black. Not a candle, not a flashlight.
كان ظلام حالكا ، لا شمعة ولاحتى كاشف ضوئي
And that hospital could have afforded flashlights.
وكان بإستطاعة المستشفى توفير كاشف ضوئي
They could have afforded to purchase these things, but they didn't.
بإستطاعتهم شراء هذه الأشياء ولكنهم لم يفعلوا
And it happened twice.
حدث ذلك مرتان
Another time, she watched in horror as nurses watched a patient die
وفي وقت آخر . شاهدت وهي تشعر بالرعب الممرضات يشاهدن مريض وهو يحتضر
because they refused to give her oxygen that they had.
لأنهن رفضن أن يعطينه الأوكسجين الذي بحوزتهن
And so three months later,
وبعد ثلاثة اشهر
just before she returned to the United States,
قبل ان تعود إلى الولايات المتحدة
nurses in Accra go on strike.
قامت الممرضات في اكرا بعمل إضراب
And her recommendation is
قامت بتقديم توصية ان
take this opportunity to fire everyone, start all over again.
يستغلوا هذه الفرصة لطردهم جميعا والبدء من جديد
Start all over again.
البدء من جديد
Now what does this have to do with leadership?
ما دخل هذا بالقيادة ؟
You see, the folks at the ministry of health,
كما ترون فإن أخطاء وزارة الصحة
the hospital administrators, the doctors, the nurses --
و إدارة المستشفى و الأطباء والممرضات
they are among just five percent of their peers
وهم من ضمن 5 % فقط من اقرانهم
who get an education after secondary school.
الذين يواصلون التعليم بعد الثانوية العامة
They are the elite. They are our leaders.
هم النخبة ،، هم قادتنا
Their decisions, their actions matter.
قراراتهم و أفعالهم مهمة
And when they fail, a nation literally suffers.
وعندما يفشلون فإن الأمة تعاني بالفعل
So when I speak of leadership,
ولذلك عندما اتكلم عن القيادة
I'm not talking about just political leaders.
أنا لا أتكلم عن القادة السياسيين فقط
We've heard a lot about that.
فلقد سمعنا الكثير عنهم
I'm talking about the elite.
انا أقصد النخبة
Those who've been trained,
هؤلاء الذين تدربوا
whose job it is to be the guardians of their society.
ووظيفتهم هي حماية المجتمع
The lawyers, the judges, the policemen, the doctors,
المحامون والقضاة ورجال الشرطة والأطباء
the engineers, the civil servants --
المهندسون والموظفون المدنيون
those are the leaders.
هؤلاء هم قادتنا
And we need to train them right.
ويجب علينا تدريبهم جيدا
Now, my first pointed and memorable experience with leadership in Ghana
أول تجربة قاسية مع القيادة في غانا
occurred when I was 16 years old.
عندما كنت في السادسة عشر من عمري
We had just had a military coup,
ووقتها حدث إنقلاب عسكري
and soldiers were pervasive in our society.
و الجنود كانوا مخترقين في مجتمعنا
They were a pervasive presence.
كان لهم حضور مخترق
And one day I go to the airport to meet my father,
وفي يومٍ ما ذهبت للمطار لملاقاة والدي
and as I walk up this grassy slope from the car park
و عندما مشيت على الجزء المكسو بالعشب من موقف السيارات
to the terminal building,
متجها إلى مبنى الوصول
I'm stopped by two soldiers wielding AK-47 assault weapons.
أوقفاني جنديان معهم اسلحة AK-47
And they asked me to join a crowd of people
وطلبوا مني أن انظم لحشد من الناس
that were running up and down this embankment.
يركضون صعودا ونزولا لمرتفع ترابي
Why? Because the path I had taken was considered out of bounds.
لماذا ؟ لأن الطريق الذي سلكته يعتبر خارج الحدود
No sign to this effect.
لا علامة تدل على ذلك
Now, I was 16. I was very worried about
وقتها كان عمري 16 عاما وكنت قلقا جدا
what my peers at school might think
حيال ما سوف يظنه بي أقراني في المدرسة
if they saw me running up and down this hill.
عندما يشاهدوني أركض أعلى وأسفل التل
I was especially concerned of what the girls might think.
و كنت قلقا خصوصا حيال ما ستظنه في الفتيات
And so I started to argue with these men.
لذلك تجادلت مع هؤلاء الرجال
It was a little reckless, but you know, I was 16.
كان طيشا قليلا و لكن كما تعلمون كنت في السادسة عشر
I got lucky.
كنت محظوظا
A Ghana Airways pilot falls into the same predicament.
هبط طيار تابع لخطوط غانا الجويه في نفس منطقتي
Because of his uniform they speak to him differently,
تحدثوا معه بشكل مختلف بسبب زيه
and they explain to him that they're just following orders.
وشرحوا له بأنهم يتبعون الأوامر
So he takes their radio, talks to their boss,
فأخذ مذياعهم و كلم رئيسهم
and gets us all released.
و تم اطلاق سراحنا جميعا
What lessons would you take from an experience like this?
ما الدروس التي تعلمتها انت من تجربة كهذه ؟
Several, for me.
بالنسبة لي دروس عديدة
Leadership matters. Those men are following
ان القيادة مهمة . وأن هؤلاء الرجال يتبعون الأوامر
the orders of a superior officer.
من رؤساهم المباشرين
I learned something about courage.
وتعلمت شيئا عن الشجاعة
It was important not to look at those guns.
وكان من المهم عدم النظر إلى المسدسات
And I also learned that it can be helpful to think about girls.
وتعلمت انه قد يكون مفيدا التفكير بالبنات
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
So a few years after this event, I leave Ghana on a scholarship
لذلك وبعد سنوات قليلة من هذا الحدث ، غادرت غانا لبعثة دراسية
to go to Swarthmore College for my education.
إلى كلية سوارثمور لإكمال دراستي
It was a breath of fresh air.
كانت بمثابة نفحة هواء لي
You know, the faculty there didn't want us to memorize information
هل تعلمون بأن أعضاء هيئة التدريس لم يريدوا منا ان نحفظ المعلومات
and repeat back to them as I was used to back in Ghana.
و نرددها من بعدهم كما كنا نفعل في غانا
They wanted us to think critically.
بل أرادوا منا ان نفكر بتحليل
They wanted us to be analytical.
أرادوا من انا نكون محليلين
They wanted us to be concerned about social issues.
أرادوا منا ان نكون مهمتمين بالقضايا الأجتماعية
In my economics classes I got high marks
وفي محاضرات الاقتصاد حصلت على درجات عالية
for my understanding of basic economics.
وذلك بسبب فهمي لأساسيات الأقتصاد
But I learned something more profound than that,
ولكني تعلمت شيئا اعمق من ذلك
which is that the leaders -- the managers of Ghana's economy --
وهو أن القادة " مدراء إقتصاد غانا "
were making breathtakingly bad decisions
كانوا يتخذون قرارات سيئة جدا
that had brought our economy to the brink of collapse.
والتي حدت بأقتصادنا إلى حافة الأنهيار
And so here was this lesson again -- leadership matters.
وبذلك عدنا مجددا لدرسنا هذا - القيادة مهمة
It matters a great deal.
إنها تهم بشكل كبير
But I didn't really fully understand what had happened to me at Swarthmore.
ولكني لم أستوعب بشكل كامل ما حدث لي في سوذرمور .
I had an inkling,
كانت فكرة غامضة
but I didn't fully realize it until I went out into the workplace
ولكني لم استوعبها بالكامل حتى ذهبت إلى مكان العمل
and I went to work at Microsoft Corporation.
ذهبت للعمل في شركة مايكروسوفت
And I was part of this team -- this thinking, learning team
وكنت جزءا من هذا الفريق -- فريق التفكير والتعلم
whose job it was to design and implement new software
والتي وظيفته هي تصميم و تطبيق برامج جديدة
that created value in the world.
والتي تصنع قيمة في العالم.
And it was brilliant to be part of this team.
كان شيئا خلاقا ان اكون جزءا من هذا الفريق
It was brilliant.
كان باهراَ
And I realized just what had happened to me at Swarthmore,
و لقد ادركت حينها ما حدث لي في سورثمور
this transformation --
هذا التحول
the ability to confront problems, complex problems,
القدرة على مواجهة المشكلة والمشاكل العويصة
and to design solutions to those problems.
وتصميم الحلول لهذه المشاكل
The ability to create is the most empowering thing
القدرة على الإبداع هي أكثر الأمور قوة
that can happen to an individual.
والتي يمكن ان تحدث للفرد
And I was part of that.
وانا كنت جزءا من ذلك
Now, while I was at Microsoft, the annual revenues of that company
والآن ، وبينما انا في مايكروسوفت فإن العائد السنوي لهذه الشركة
grew larger than the GDP of the Republic of Ghana.
ينمو أكبر من الناتج المحلي الإجمالي لجمهورية غانا
And by the way, it's continued to.
و بالمناسبة فإنها مستمرة في ذلك
The gap has widened since I left.
الفجوة إتسعت منذ ان غادرت
Now, I've already spoken about one of the reasons why this has occurred.
الآن وقد تكلمت آنفا بخصوص أحد هذه الأسباب ولماذا حدث
I mean, it's the people there who are so hardworking,
أنا اقصد الشعب هناك اللذين يكدحون بشدة
persistent, creative, empowered.
و يثابرون ويبدعون و المفوضين
But there were also some external factors:
ولكن كان هناك بعض العوامل الخارجية :
free markets, the rule of law, infrastructure.
الأسواق الحرة و دور القانون و البنى التحتية
These things were provided by institutions
وهذه الاشياء قدمتها المؤسسات
run by the people that I call leaders.
التي يديرها الناس والذي اسميهم قادة
And those leaders did not emerge spontaneously.
وهؤلاء القادة لم ينشأوا عفويا
Somebody trained them to do the work that they do.
فقد دربهم شخصا ما لينجزوا اعمالهم التي يفعلوها
Now, while I was at Microsoft, this funny thing happened.
وعندما كنت اعمل في مايكروسوفت حدث شيء مضحك ،
I became a parent.
اصبحت أباً
And for the first time, Africa mattered more to me than ever before.
و لآول مرة ، أفريقا اصبحت تهم اكثر من اي وقت مضى
Because I realized that the state of the African continent
لأني ادركت ان حالة قارة افريقيا
would matter to my children and their children.
سوف تحدث فرقا لأولادي وأولادهم
That the state of the world -- the state of the world
العالم كله ، فالعالم بأكمله
depends on what's happening to Africa,
يعتمد على ما يحدث في افريقيا
as far as my kids would be concerned.
بقدر ما سيهتم أطفالي
And at this time, when I was going through
و في هذا الوقت عندما كنت امر خلال
what I call my "pre-mid-life crisis,"
ما اسميه " ازمة ما قبل منتصف العمر " الخاصة بي
Africa was a mess.
افريقا كانت فوضى
Somalia had disintegrated into anarchy.
الصومال أنحل إلى فوضى
Rwanda was in the throes of this genocidal war.
رواند عانت ويلات الحرب الجماعية
And it seemed to me that that was the wrong direction,
و بدى لي بأنهم يتجهون إلى الإتجاه الخاطئ
and I needed to be back helping.
و يتوجب علي العودة للمساعدة
I couldn't just stay in Seattle and raise my kids
لم استطع ان ابقى في سياتل و ان اربي اطفالي
in an upper-middle class neighborhood and feel good about it.
في حي من الطبقة المتوسطة العليا و أن اشعر بالرضى لذلك
This was not the world that I'd want my children to grow up in.
لم يكن هذا العالم الذي اريد ان يكبر اولادي فيه
So I decided to get engaged, and the first thing that I did
لذلك قررت ان اشارك و أول ما فعلته هو
was to come back to Ghana and talk with a lot of people
الرجوع إلى غانا و التحدث مع الكثير من الأشخاص
and really try to understand what the real issues were.
و المحاولة الجادة لمعرفة ماهي القضايا الفعلية
And three things kept coming up for every problem:
وواجهتني ثلاثة امور في كل مشكلة
corruption, weak institutions
الفساد و المؤسسات الضعيفة
and the people who run them -- the leaders.
و الأناس الذين يقودونها -- القادة
Now, I was a little scared
الآن كنت خائفاً قليلا
because when you see those three problems,
لأنه عندما تواجه هذه المشاكل الثلاث
they seem really hard to deal with.
فإنه يبدوا من الصعب التعامل معها
And they might say, "Look, don't even try."
و قد يقولوا انظر لا تفكر ولو حتى بالمحاولة
But, for me, I asked the question,
و لكني سألت السؤال
"Well, where are these leaders coming from?
" حسنا ، من أين يأتون هؤلاء القادة ؟
What is it about Ghana that produces leaders
وماذا عن غانا التي يخرج منها القادة
that are unethical or unable to solve problems?"
غير الأخلاقيين و غير القادرين لحل المشاكل ؟ "
So I went to look at what was happening in our educational system.
لذلك ذهبت للنظر في ما يحدث في نظامنا التعليمي
And it was the same -- learning by rote --
وكان هو نفسه -- التعليم عن طريق الحفظ عن ظهر قلب-
from primary school through graduate school.
من المدرسة الإبتدائية حتى فوق الجامعي.
Very little emphasis on ethics,
قليل من التركيز على الأخلاق
and the typical graduate
و المتوسط كما تعلمون هم المتخرجون النموذجيون
from a university in Ghana has a stronger sense
من جامعة في غانا لديهم حس اقوى
of entitlement than a sense of responsibility.
في الإستحقاق أكثر من الإحساس بالمسؤولية
This is wrong.
وهذا غلط
So I decided to engage this particular problem.
لذلك قررت أن اشترك في هذه المشكلة بالتحديد
Because it seems to me that every society, every society,
لأنه يبدوا لي ان كل مجتمع ، كل مجتمع ،
must be very intentional about how it trains its leaders.
يجب ان يكون هادفاً حول كيفية تدريب هؤلاء القادة
And Ghana was not paying enough attention.
و غانا لم تكن تعطي ذلك الإهتمام الكافي
And this is true across sub-Saharan Africa, actually.
وفي الواقع هذة حقيقة مشتركة في أفريقا جنوب الصحراء.
So this is what I'm doing now.
إذاً هذا ما أفعله الآن
I'm trying to bring the experience that I had at Swarthmore to Africa.
أحاول ان اجلب التجربة التي عشتها في سورذمور إلى افريقيا
I wish there was a liberal arts college in every African country.
أتمنى لو كان هناك كلية أداب حرة في كل دولة أفريقية
I think it would make a huge difference.
أعتقد ان من شأنها إحداث إختلاف كبير
And what Ashesi University is trying to do
وما تحاول جامعة " Ashesi" فعله هو
is to train a new generation of ethical, entrepreneurial leaders.
هو تدريب جيل جديد من القادة الأخلاقيين والرواد في الأعمال
We're trying to train leaders of exceptional integrity,
فنحن نحاول تدريب قادة أصحاب كرامة استثنائية
who have the ability to confront the complex problems,
والذين لديهم القدرة على مواجهة المشاكل المعقدة
ask the right questions, and come up with workable solutions.
و طرح الأسئلة المناسبة و إيجاد الحلول العملية.
I'll admit that there are times when it seems like "Mission: Impossible,"
سأعترف بأن هناك اوقات يبدو فيها انه " ضرب من المستحيل "
but we must believe that these kids are smart.
ولكن يجب ان نؤمن بأن هؤلاء الأطفال أذكياء
That if we involve them in their education,
ويحدث ذلك إذا تدخلنا في تعليمهم
if we have them discuss the real issues that they confront --
و إذا جعلناهم يناقشون المشاكل الحقيقية التي يواجهونها
that our whole society confronts --
والتي يواجهها المجتمع بأكمله
and if we give them skills that enable them to engage the real world,
و إذا أعطيناهم المهارة التي تفتح لهم الطريق بالإشتراك في العالم الحقيقي
that magic will happen.
فحينها سوف نصل إلى مرادنا
Now, a month into this project, we'd just started classes.
الآن ، وبعد مضي شهر منذ بدأ هذا المشروع ، بدأنا محاضراتنا
And a month into it, I come to the office,
و بعد شهر من هذه المحاضرات قدمت إلى المكتب
and I have this email from one of our students.
ووجدت رسالة من أحد طلابنا
And it said, very simply, "I am thinking now."
و قال فيها ببساطة " أنا أفكر الآن " .
And he signs off, "Thank you."
ووقع " شكرا لك "
It's such a simple statement.
إنه تصريح بسيط
But I was moved almost to tears
و لكنه اثر في لدرجة أني كدت ابكي
because I understood what was happening to this young man.
لأني فهمت ما حدث لهذا الشاب
And it is an awesome thing to be a part
وهو شيئ جميل ان تكون جزء
of empowering someone in this way.
من تمكين شخص ما بهذه الطريقة
I am thinking now.
و انا افكر الآن
This year we challenged our students
هذه السنة تحدينا طلابنا
to craft an honor code themselves.
في خلق ميثاق شرف لهم انفسهم
There's a very vibrant debate going on on campus now
حصل نقاش حماسي جدا في بهو الجامعة الآن
over whether they should have an honor code,
حول ما إذا كان يتوجب حصولهم على ميثاق شرف،
and if so, what it should look like.
و إذا كان يتوجب ذلك ، بأي شكل يجيب ان يكون
One of the students asked a question that just warmed my heart.
سألت أحدى الطالبات سؤالاً أثلج صدري
Can we create a perfect society?
هل يمكننا خلق مجتمع مثالي ؟
Her understanding that a student-crafted honor code
كان فهمها أن ميثاقاً شرفيا للطلاب
constitutes a reach towards perfection is incredible.
يتضمن الوصول إلى الكمال وهذا غير معقول
Now, we cannot achieve perfection,
الآن ، نحن لا يمكننا تحقيق الكمال
but if we reach for it, then we can achieve excellence.
ولكن إذا وصلنا له حينها نستطيع الوصول إلى الامتياز
I don't know ultimately what they will do.
ليس لدي أدنى خلفية عن ماذا سيفعلون
I don't know whether they will decide to have this honor code.
لا أعلم ما إذا كانوا سيقررون الحصول على رمز شرفي
But the conversation they're having now --
ولكن مناقشاتهم الجارية الآن
about what their good society should look like,
حول كيف يجب أن يكون مجتمعهم الجيد
what their excellent society should look like,
وكيف يبدوا مجتمعهم الممتاز
is a really good thing.
إنه فعلا شيئ جميل
Am I out of time? OK.
هل أنتهى وقتي ؟ حسنا
Now, I just wanted to leave that slide up
الآن ، أريد فقط ان اترك هذه الشريحة معلقة
because it's important that we think about it.
لأنه من المهم أن نفكر بها
I'm very excited about the fact
أنا متحمس جدا حول حقيقة
that every student at Ashesi University does community service before they graduate.
ان كل طالب في جامعة ashesi يقوم بأعمال لخدمة المجتمع قبل التخرج
That for many of them, it has been a life-altering experience.
وهذه التجربة غيرت حياة العديد منهم
These young future leaders are beginning to understand
قادة المستقبل بدأو بفهم
the real business of leadership,
المغزى الرئيسي من القيادة
the real privilege of leadership,
الإمتياز الحقيقي للقيادة
which is after all to serve humanity.
هو خدمة الإنسانية
I am even more thrilled by the fact that least year
وأنا اكثر حماسة بحقيقة ان السنة الماضية
our student body elected a woman
مجلس الطلاب انتخب أمرأة
to be the head of Student Government.
لتصبح رئيسة الحكومة الطلابية
It's the first time in the history of Ghana
وهذه تعد المرة الأولى في تاريخ غانا
that a woman has been elected head of Student Government
التي تنتخب فيها إمراة لتصبح رئيسة حكومة الطلاب
at any university.
في أي جامعة
It says a lot about her.
وهذا يعكس الكثير عنها
It says a lot about the culture that's forming on campus.
ويعكس الكثير حول التحوّل الثقافي في البهو الجامعي
It says a lot about her peers who elected her.
ويعكس الكثير عن اقرانها الذين انتخبوها
She won with 75 percent of the vote.
فقد فازت بنسبة 75 % من الأصوات
And it gives me a lot of hope.
وأعطتني المزيد من الآمل
It turns out that corporate West Africa
وأتضح ان مؤسسة أفريقيا الغربية
also appreciates what's happening with our students.
تحيي ايضا ما حدث لهؤلاء الطلبة
We've graduated two classes of students to date.
لقد خرجنا دفعتين من الطلاب حتى الآن
And every single one of them has been placed.
و كل منهم استقر
And we're getting great reports back
و تصلنا تقارير عظيمة عنهم
from corporate Ghana, corporate West Africa,
من مؤسسة غانا و مؤسسة افريقيا الغربية
and the things that they're most impressed about is work ethic.
والشيء الذي أعجبوا في هو العمل الأخلاقي
You know, that passion for what they're doing.
كما تعلم فهذا ولعهم بالشيء الذين يقومون به
The persistence, their ability to deal with ambiguity,
الإصرار و الإرادة للتعامل مع الغموض
their ability to tackle problems that they haven't seen before.
وقدرتهم لمواجهة المشاكل التي لم يروها من قبل
This is good because
وهذا جيد لأن كما تعلمون
over the past five years, there have been times
خلال السنوات الخمس الماضية كانت هناك اوقات
when I've felt this is "Mission: Impossible."
أحسست بأن هذا " ضرب من المستحيل "
And it's just wonderful to see these glimmers
و انه لمن الجميل ان ترى مثل هذه الومضات
of the promise of what can happen if we train our kids right.
من الأمل الذي يحدث لو ان اطفالنا تدربوا بشكل جيد
I think that the current and future leaders of Africa
أعتقد بأن القادة الحاليين والمستقبليين لأفريقيا
have an incredible opportunity
لديهم فرص غير معقولة
to drive a major renaissance on the continent.
لتوجيه النهضة العملاقة في القارة
It's an incredible opportunity.
وهذه فرصة غير معقولة
There aren't very many more opportunities like this in the world.
ولا توجد فرص كهذة كثيرة في العالم
I believe that Africa has reached an inflection point
أؤمن أن افريقا وصلت نقطة التحول
with a march of democracy and free markets across the continent.
وبمسيرة ديموقراطية و أسواق مفتوحة عبر القارة
We have reached a moment from which can emerge
توصلنا إلى اللحظة التي تندمج فيها
a great society within one generation.
مجتمع عظيم في جيل واحد
It will depend on inspired leadership.
والتي يعتمد على القيادة الملهمة
And it is my contention that the manner in which we train our leaders
وهذا هو نضالي نحو تدريب قادتنا
will make all the difference.
والذي يحدث كل الفروق
Thank you, and God bless.
شكرا لكم ، بارككم الله
(Applause)
( تصفيق )